Federation of Citizens Associations of the District of Columbia 028
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Federation of Citizens Associations of the District of Columbia Records
1964-1987
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Federation of Citizens Associations of the District of Columbia
028
4.5 Linear feet
12 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Office Files, 1964-1973 (1.25 linear ft.) This series consists of the Federation's office files which document its daily operations. It includes correspondence, minutes, lists, handwritten notes, resolutions, motions, charts, pamphlets, and flyers. Series 2: Correspondence, 1975-1987 (. 5 linear ft.) The series contains correspondence (1975-1980) (with any relevant attachments) sent to and from Nancy Wright, Secretary of the Federation at the time, primarily from local D.C. and federal government officials. Letters to and from the Federation are grouped in folders separately. The remaining correspondence is arranged chronologically. Series 3: Meeting Minutes, 1969-1990 (1 linear ft.) This series contains minutes of meetings of the Federation that are arranged chronologically by date of the meeting. It also includes materials related to or gathered in preparation for the meeting. Series 4: Resolutions, 1975-1987 (.25 linear ft.) The series contains formal resolutions passed by the Federation and its member organizations during meetings. Background documents such as correspondence, meeting minutes, clippings, legislation, statements before the City Council and Congress, and notes related to the resolution are also included. The resolutions were used as policy statements and covered issues such as transportation, development, zoning, education, D.C. government finances, election law, crime, and D.C. General Hospital.br> Series 5: Topical Files, 1950-1987 (1.50 linear ft.) This series contains correspondence, resolutions, financial materials, Federation certifications, citizen association newsletters, directories, clippings, and reference materials arranged in folders alphabetically by content or topic.
Biographical / Historical
In March 1910, representatives from 22 established citizens' associations met to form an alliance to represent their combined interests before Congress, the President, and the D.C. government. William Clayton, Allen Davis, and Charles Lancaster were some of the key founders of the Federation. Throughout its history, the Federation has championed a number of interests, including establishment of the Public Utilities Commission, D.C. congressional representation as well as issues affecting transportation, police, fire, fiscal matters, environment, and education in the city. Historically, the membership of citizens associations has been white.
Custodial History
The records of the Federation of Citizens Association of the District of Columbia were donated to the Archives in 1989 by Nancy Wright, Secretary of the Federation.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of financial information, correspondence, meeting minutes, internal memoranda, resolutions, directories, reports, resolutions, and clippings maintained by the Federation of Citizens Association of the District of Columbia. Major topics covered include city planning and zoning, historical preservation, election law, D.C. government budgets, transportation, and crime.
Neighborhoods; Organizational Records; Community organization; Minutes (Records); Correspondence; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc); Citizens' Associations; Politics and government; Community development, Urban
- Series 1: Office Files, 1964-1973
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of the Federation's office files which document its daily operations. It includes correspondence, minutes, lists, handwritten notes, resolutions, motions, charts, pamphlets, and flyers.
  - Office Files, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Office Files, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Office Files, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Office Files, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Office Files, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Office Files, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Office Files, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Office Files, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Office Files, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Office Files, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Office Files, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Office Files, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1975-1987
  The series contains correspondence (1975-1980) (with any relevant attachments) sent to and from Nancy Wright, Secretary of the Federation at the time, primarily from local D.C. and federal government officials. Letters "to" and "from" the Federation are grouped in folders separately; the remaining correspondence is loosely arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence sent by Committee Chairmen, 1975-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letters received, 1975-1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from the Federation, 1980-1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to the Federation, 1981-1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to the Federation, 1981-1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Meeting Minutes, 1969-1990
  This series contains minutes of meetings of the Federation that are arranged chronologically by date of the meeting. It also includes materials related to or gathered in preparation for the meeting.
  - Meetings background and notes, 1969-1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Meetings background and notes, 1969-1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Meetings background and notes, 1969-1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Meetings background and notes, 1969-1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Meetings background and notes, 1969-1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series 4: Resolutions, 1975-1987
  The series contains formal resolutions passed by the Federation and its member organizations during meetings. Background documents such as correspondence, meeting minutes, clippings, legislation, statements before the City Council and Congress, and notes related to the resolution are also included. The resolution were used as policy statements and covered issues such as transportation, development, zoning, education, D.C. government finances, election law, crime, and D.C. General Hospital.
  - Resolutions, 1975-1987 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Series 5: Topical Files, 1950-1987
  This series contains correspondence, resolutions, financial materials, Federation certifications, citizen association newsletters, directories, clippings, and reference materials arranged in folders alphabetically by content or topic.
  - Annual Dinners, 1968-1972 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Attendance Record, 1972-1975 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Budget, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Budget, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Certification, 1977-1984 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Certification, 1977-1984 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Citations, 1976-1983 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - City Planning and Zoning, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - City Planning and Zoning, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Committee materials, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Committee preference sheets, 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Congress on zoning, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Directory, 1969-1987 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Directory, 1969-1987 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Directory, 1969-1987 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Directory, 1969-1987 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Fiscal Relations and Taxation Committee, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Fiscal Relations and Taxation Committee, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Federation Home Rule Activities, 1969-1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Michigan Park Citizens Association, 1978-1987 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters - Burleith, 1973-1979 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters - Foggy Bottom, 1978-1980 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters - Olivet Heights, 1973-1975 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Potomac River Basin, 1967-1969 (Box 12, Folder 7)